Hello. My name is Jarrett Krosoczka,
مرحباً، إسمي جاريت كريزوسكا
and I write and illustrate books for children for a living.
و أنا أكتب و أشرح الكتب للأطفال لكسب عيشي.
So I use my imagination as my full-time job.
لذا أستخدم خيالي كوظيفة بدوام كامل.
But well before my imagination was my vocation,
لكن في السابق كان خيالي هو إجازتي،
my imagination saved my life.
خيالي أنقذ حياتي.
When I was a kid, I loved to draw,
عندما كنت صغيراً، كنت أحب أن أرسم،
and the most talented artist I knew
و أكثر فنان موهوب عرفته هو
was my mother,
كانت أمي
but my mother was addicted to heroin.
لكن أمي كانت مدمنة على الهيروين.
And when your parent is a drug addict,
وعندما يكون والدك مدمن على المخدرات،
it's kind of like Charlie Brown trying to kick the football,
فهو بطريقة ما مثل محاولة شارلي براون لتسديد الكرة،
because as much as you want to love on that person,
لأنه على قدر ماتريد أن تحب ذلك الشخص،
as much as you want to receive love from that person,
بقدر ماتريد أن تتلقى الحب من ذلك الشخص،
every time you open your heart, you end up on your back.
كل مرة تفتح قلبك، تنتهي على قفاك.
So throughout my childhood, my mother was incarcerated
لذا خلال طفولتي، أمي كانت مسجونة
and I didn't have my father because
و لم أحصل على أبي لأني
I didn't even learn his first name until I was in the sixth grade.
لم أتعلم حتى اسمه الأول إلا عندما أصبحت في الصف السادس
But I had my grandparents,
لكن كان لدي أجدادي
my maternal grandparents Joseph and Shirley,
جدي الأموميين جوزيف و شيرلي،
who adopted me just before my third birthday
الذين تبنوني قبل ميلادي الثالث بقليل
and took me in as their own,
و أخذوني كحفيد حقيقي لهم،
after they had already raised five children.
بعد أن كانوا قد ربوا خمسة أطفال.
So two people who grew up in the Great Depression,
إذن شخصين نشأوا في الكساد الكبير،
there in the very, very early '80s took on a new kid.
هم في في بدايات الثمانينات اسقبلوا طفل جديد.
I was the Cousin Oliver of the sitcom
كنت مثل ابن العم أوليفر لمسرحية سيتكوم
of the Krosoczka family,
لعائلة الكريزوسكا،
the new kid who came out of nowhere.
الطفل الجديد الذي ظهر من العدم
And I would like to say that life was totally easy with them.
ويجب أن أقول أن الحياة كانت سهلة تماماً معهم
They each smoked two packs a day, each, nonfiltered,
كل منهما يدخن علبتين كل يوم، بدون مصفاة،
and by the time I was six,
وعندما وصل عمري ستة سنوات،
I could order a Southern Comfort Manhattan,
كان بإمكاني طلب مانهاتن الجنوبي المريح،
dry with a twist, rocks on the side,
وجاف مع لفة، الصخورعلى الجانب،
the ice on the side so you could fit more liquor in the drink.
الثلج على الجانب حتى يتلائم أكثر مع الخمر في الشراب
But they loved the hell out of me. They loved me so much.
لكنهم أحبوني بجنون. أحبوني كثيراً
And they supported my creative efforts,
ودعموا جهودي الإبداعية،
because my grandfather was a self-made man.
لأن جدي كان شخص كون نفسه بنفسه
He ran and worked in a factory.
ذهب وعمل في مصنع
My grandmother was a homemaker.
جدتي كانت ربة منزل
But here was this kid who loved Transformers
لكن هنا وجد ذلك الطفل الذي أحب "Transformers" المتحولون
and Snoopy and the Ninja Turtles,
و ال"سنوبي" المتطفلين و سلاحف النينجا،
and the characters that I read about, I fell in love with,
و الشخصيات التي قرأت عنها، وقعت في حبها
and they became my friends.
و أصبحوا أصدقائي.
So my best friends in life were the characters
لذا أفضل أصدقائي في الحياة كانوا الشخصيات
I read about in books.
التي قرأت عنها في الكتب.
I went to Gates Lane Elementary School in Worcester, Massachusetts,
ذهبت إلى مدرسة جايت لان الإبتدائية في وركستر ماسوتشوستس
and I had wonderful teachers there,
حظيت بمعلمين رائعين هناك،
most notably in first grade Mrs. Alisch.
الأكثر بروزاً في الصف الأول السيدة أليش.
And I just, I can just remember the love that she offered
و أستطيع أن أتذكر فقط الحب الذي قدمته
us as her students.
لنا نحن طلابها.
When I was in the third grade,
عندما كنت في الصف الثالث،
a monumental event happened.
حدث ضخم حصل.
An author visited our school, Jack Gantos.
كاتب زار مدرستنا، جاك جانتوس.
A published author of books came to talk to us
كاتب نشر كتب، أتى ليكلمنا
about what he did for a living.
عن ماذا يعمل حتى يعيل نفسه.
And afterwards, we all went back to our classrooms
وبعد ذلك، كلنا عدنا إلى غرف الصف
and we drew our own renditions of his main character,
و رسمنا نسختنا الفنية لشخصيته الرئيسية،
Rotten Ralph.
روتن رالف.
And suddenly the author appeared in our doorway,
وفجأة الكاتب ظهر على بابنا،
and I remember him sort of sauntering down the aisles,
و أتذكره يتجول في الممرات،
going from kid to kid looking at the desks, not saying a word.
من طفل لطفل ناظراً إلى طاولاتهم، بدون أن يقول أي كلمة.
But he stopped next to my desk,
لكنه توقف عند طاولتي
and he tapped on my desk, and he said,
و نقر على طاولتي، وقال،
"Nice cat." (Laughter)
"قطة لطيفة." (ضحك)
And he wandered away.
ثم ذهب مبتعداً.
Two words that made a colossal difference in my life.
كلمتين فرق ضخم في حياتي.
When I was in the third grade, I wrote a book for the first time,
عندما كنت في الصف الثالث، كتبت كتاب للمرة الأولى،
"The Owl Who Thought He Was The Best Flyer." (Laughter)
"البومة التي اعتقد أنه أفضل طائر." (ضحك)
We had to write our own Greek myth,
كان يجب علينا أن نكتب أساطيرنا اليونانية الخاصة بنا،
our own creation story, so I wrote a story about an owl
قصتنا التي ننشئها بأنفسنا، لذلك كتبت عن البومة
who challenged Hermes to a flying race,
التي تحدت هرمس (مراسل الآلهة اليونان) لسباق طيران،
and the owl cheated,
لكن البومة غشت،
and Hermes, being a Greek god, grew angry and bitter,
وهرمس، كونه آلهة يوناني، زاد غضبه ومرارته،
and turned the owl into a moon,
وحول البومة إلى قمر،
so the owl had to live the rest of his life as a moon
لذا فإن البومة كان عليها أن تعيش بقية حياتها كقمر
while he watched his family and friends play at night.
بينما يراقب عائلته و أصدقاءه يلعبون في الليل.
Yeah. (Laughter)
ياه. (ضحك)
My book had a title page.
كتابي كان به صفحة عنوان.
I was clearly worried about my intellectual property when I was eight.
واضح أني كنت قلق بخصوص حقوقي الفكرية عندما كان عمري ثمانية سنين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it was a story that was told with words and pictures,
و كانت قصة تقص بالكلمات والصور،
exactly what I do now for a living,
تماماً ما أفعله الآن لعيشي،
and I sometimes let the words have the stage on their own,
و أحيانا أترك الكلمات تعتلي المسرح وحدها
and sometimes I allowed the pictures to work on their own
و أحياناً أسمح للصور أن تعمل بنفسها
to tell the story.
وتحكي القصة
My favorite page is the "About the author" page.
صفحة المفضلة هي صفحة "عن الكاتب".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I learned to write about myself in third person
إذا تعلمت الكتابة عن نفسي كشخص ثالث
at a young age.
في سن صغير.
So I love that last sentence: "He liked making this book."
لذا أنا أحب هذه العبارة: "أحب صنع هذا الكتاب."
And I liked making that book because I loved using my imagination,
وأحببت صنع ذلك الكتاب لأني أحببت استخدام مخيلتي،
and that's what writing is.
وتلك هي الكتابة
Writing is using your imagination on paper,
الكتابة هي استخدام تخيلك على الورق،
and I do get so scared because I travel to so many schools now
وأخاف كثيراً لأني أذهب إلى العديد من المدارس حالياً
and that seems like such a foreign concept to kids,
و يبدو هذا كمفهوم أجنبي للأطفال
that writing would be using your imagination on paper,
أن الكتابة تكون استخدام مخيلتك على الورق،
if they're allowed to even write now within the school hours.
إذا سمح لهم حتى بالكتابة خلال ساعات الدراسة.
So I loved writing so much that I'd come home from school,
لذا أحببت الكتابة جداً لدرجة أني أعود للبيت من المدرسة،
and I would take out pieces of paper,
و أخرج قطع ورقية،
and I would staple them together,
و أشبكها ببعضها،
and I would fill those blank pages with words and pictures
و أملأ تلك الصفحات الفارغة بكلمات وصور
just because I loved using my imagination.
فقط لأني أحببت استخدام مخيلتي.
And so these characters would become my friends.
حتى تصبح تلك الشخصيات أصدقائي.
There was an egg, a tomato, a head of lettuce and a pumpkin,
كان هناك بيضة، و طماطة، ورأس خسة و يقطينه،
and they all lived in this refrigerator city,
و كلهم كانوا يعيشون في مدينة الثلاجة،
and in one of their adventures they went to a haunted house
و في إحدى مغامراتهم ذهبوا إلى منزل مهجور
that was filled with so many dangers
كان مليء بالمخاطر
like an evil blender who tried to chop them up,
كخلاط شرير حاول أن يقطعهم،
an evil toaster who tried to kidnap the bread couple,
و محمصة شريرة حاولت أن تخطف ثنائي الخبز،
and an evil microwave who tried to melt their friend
و مايكرويف شرير حاول أن يذوّب صديقهم
who was a stick of butter. (Laughter)
والذي كان قطعة من الزبدة. (ضحك)
And I'd make my own comics too,
و قد أصنع قصص هزلية خاصة بي،
and this was another way for me to tell stories,
و تلك كانت طريقة أخرى لي حتى أحكي القصص،
through words and through pictures.
خلال الكلمات والصور.
Now when I was in sixth grade,
الآن عندما أصبحت في الصف السادس،
the public funding all but eliminated the arts budgets
التمويل العام دعم كل شيء ماعدا ميزانية الفن
in the Worcester public school system.
في نظام مدرسة (وركست) العامة.
I went from having art once a week
تغير الموضوع بحيث أصبحت بدلاً من تلقي درس الفن مرة كل إسبوع
to twice a month
أصبح مرتين في الشهر
to once a month to not at all.
ثم مرة في الشهر حتى أصبحنا لا نأخذ حصص فن أبداً
And my grandfather, he was a wise man,
وجدي كان شخص حكيم،
and he saw that as a problem, because he knew
ورأى ذلك كمشكلة، لأنه عرف
that was, like, the one thing I had. I didn't play sports.
أنه الفن كان الشيء الوحيد الذي أستطيعه. لم أكن جيد في الرياضة.
I had art.
كان لدي الفن.
So he walked into my room one evening,
لذا مشى إلى داخل غرفتي في إحدى الأمسيات،
and he sat on the edge of my bed,
وجلس على طرف سريري،
and he said, "Jarrett, it's up to you, but if you'd like to,
وقال، "جاريت، هذا الموضوع عائد إليك لكن إن أردت
we'd like to send you to the classes at the Worcester Art Museum."
نريد أن نرسلك إلى صفوف في متحف وركستر للفنون"
And I was so thrilled.
وكنت مذهولاً
So from sixth through 12th grade,
لذا من الصف السادس حتى الصف الثاني عشر،
once, twice, sometimes three times a week,
أحياناً مرة أو مرتين أو ثلاث مرات في الأسبوع،
I would take classes at the art museum,
أخذ حصص في متحف الفنون،
and I was surrounded by other kids who loved to draw,
وكنت محاطاً بأطفال أحبوا الرسم،
other kids who shared a similar passion.
أطفال آخرين لديهم نفس الشغف.
Now my publishing career began when I designed the cover
الآن مهنتي في النشر بدأت عندما صممت غلاف
for my eighth grade yearbook,
لكتابي السنوي للصف الثامن،
and if you're wondering about the style of dress I put our mascot in,
و إذا كنت تتساءل عن نمط الثوب الذي أضعه في جالب الحظ
I was really into Bell Biv DeVoe and MC Hammer
كنت فعلاً مولع ب بيل بيف ديفو و أم سي هامر
and Vanilla Ice at the time. (Laughter)
و فانيلا أيس في ذلك الوقت. (ضحك)
And to this day, I still can do karaoke to "Ice, Ice Baby"
ولهذا اليوم، لازلت أستطيع أن أؤدي كاريوكي ل"أيس أيس بايبي"
without looking at the screen.
بدون النظر للشاشة.
Don't tempt me, because I will do it.
لاتحثوني، لأني سأفعلها.
So I get shipped off to private school,
لذا انتقلت إلى مدرسة خاصة،
K through eight, public schools, but for some reason
من الحضانة إلى الصف الثامن، مدرسة عامة، لكن لسبب ما
my grandfather was upset that somebody
جدي كان منزعج أن هناك
at the local high school had been stabbed and killed,
شخص ما في المدرسة الثانوية المحلية تم طعنه وقتله،
so he didn't want me to go there.
لذا لم يردني أن أذهب إلى هناك.
He wanted me to go to a private school, and he gave me an option.
أرادني أن أذهب لمدرسة خاصة، و أعطاني خيار.
You can go to Holy Name, which is coed,
يمكنك الذهاب إلى هولي نايم، وهي مختلطة،
or St. John's, which is all boys.
أو St. John's، وهي للأولاد فقط
Very wise man, because he knew I would,
رجل حكيم جداً، لأنه عرف أنني سأفعل،
I felt like I was making the decision on my own,
شعرت كأنني أنا من يصنع القرار بنفسي،
and he knew I wouldn't choose St. John's,
و عرف أنني لن أختار St. Johns
so I went to Holy Name High School,
لذا ذهبت لثانوية هولي نايم،
which was a tough transition because, like I said,
حيث كان ذلك تغيير صعب، بسبب مثل ما قلت،
I didn't play sports,
لم أكن ألعب الرياضة،
and it was very focused on sports,
وكانت جداً تركيزها على الرياضة،
but I took solace in Mr. Shilale's art room.
لكن وجدت العزاء في غرفة السيد شاليل للفن
And I just flourished here.
وازدهرت هنا.
I just couldn't wait to get to that classroom every day.
لم أكن أستطيع أن أنتظر الدخول لتلك الغرفة كل يوم.
So how did I make friends?
لذا كيف كنت أكون صداقات؟
I drew funny pictures of my teachers -- (Laughter) --
كنت أرسم رسمات مضحكة لمعلميني -- (ضحك)
and I passed them around.
و أمررها في الأنحاء.
Well, in English class, in ninth grade,
حسناً، في صف اللغة الإنجليزية، في الصف التاسع،
my friend John, who was sitting next to me,
صديقي جون، الذي كان يجلس بجانبي،
laughed a little bit too hard.
ضحك قليلاً بشدة.
Mr. Greenwood was not pleased.
لم يكن السيد قرين وود مسروراً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He instantly saw that I was the cause of the commotion,
رأى فوراً أني السبب في الشغب،
and for the first time in my life, I was sent to the hall,
ولأول مرة في حياتي تم إرسالي للممر،
and I thought, "Oh no, I'm doomed.
وفكرت في داخلي، " اوه لا، أنا منكوب.
My grandfather's just going to kill me."
جدي سيقتلني"
And he came out to the hallway and he said,
وجاء إلى الممر و قال
"Let me see the paper."
"دعني أرى تلك الورقة"
And I thought, "Oh no. He thinks it's a note."
وفكرت "أوه لا، يظن أنها ملاحظة"
And so I took this picture, and I handed it to him.
لذا أخذت تلك الصورة، و أعطيته إياها
And we sat in silence for that brief moment,
و جلسنا في صمت للحظة قصيرة
and he said to me,
وقال لي
"You're really talented." (Laughter)
"أنت فعلاً موهوب" (ضحك)
"You're really good. You know, the school newspaper
"أنت حقاً جيد. هل تعرف، جريدة المدرسة
needs a new cartoonist, and you should be the cartoonist.
تحتاج إلى رسام كرتوني، ويجب أن تكون رسام كرتوني.
Just stop drawing in my class."
لكن فقط توقف عن الرسم في صفي"
So my parents never found out about it.
لذا والداي لم يعرفا بذلك أبداً
I didn't get in trouble. I was introduced to Mrs. Casey,
لم أقع في ورطة. تم تقديمي للسيد كايسي،
who ran the school newspaper,
والذي يدير صحيفة المدرسة،
and I was for three and a half years
وكنت لمدة ثلاث سنين ونصف
the cartoonist for my school paper,
الرسام الكرتوني لصحيفة الدرسة،
handling such heavy issues as,
تعاملت مع قضايا ثقيلة مثل
seniors are mean,
القديمون فظين جداً
freshmen are nerds,
المستجدين دوافير،
the prom bill is so expensive. I can't believe how much it costs to go to the prom.
فاتورة حفل البروم جداً غالية. لا أصدق كم يكلف الذهاب لحفل البروم
And I took the headmaster to task
و أخذت الإدارة لتوزيع المهام
and then I also wrote an ongoing story about a boy named Wesley
و بعدها صرت أكتب قصة مستمرة عن ولد اسمه ويزلي
who was unlucky in love, and I just swore up and down
الذي كان غير محظوظ في الحب، كنت أقسم علوي سفلي
that this wasn't about me,
أنه لم تكن عني.
but all these years later it was totally me.
لكن بعد كل تلك السنين كان ذلك أنا تماماً
But it was so cool because I could write these stories,
لكن كان ذلك جداً رائع لأني أستطيع كتابة تلك القصص،
I could come up with these ideas,
أستطيع أن أبدع الأفكار
and they'd be published in the school paper,
وتنشر في صحيفة المدرسة،
and people who I didn't know could read them.
والأشخاص الذين لم أعرفهم استطاعوا قراءتها
And I loved that thought, of being able to share my ideas
و أحببت فكرة استطاعتي مشاركة أفكاري
through the printed page.
خلال الصفحة المطبوعة.
On my 14th birthday, my grandfather and my grandmother
في عيد ميلادي الرابع عشر، جدي وجدتي
gave me the best birthday present ever:
أعطوني أفضل هدية ميلاد على الإطلاق
a drafting table that I have worked on ever since.
طاولة مسودة التي مازلت أعمل عليها منذ ذلك الحين
Here I am, 20 years later,
ها أنا، بعد 20 سنة
and I still work on this table every day.
و لازلت أعمل على هذه الطاولة كل يوم
On the evening of my 14th birthday,
في مساء ميلادي الرابع عشر
I was given this table, and we had Chinese food.
أعطيت هذه الطاولة، و أكلنا طعام صيني
And this was my fortune:
وذلك كان حظي
"You will be successful in your work."
"ستكون ناجحاً في عملك"
I taped it to the top left hand of my table,
ألصقتها على أعلى اليسار على طاولتي
and as you can see, it's still there.
و كما ترون لاتزال هناك
Now I never really asked my grandparents for anything.
الآن لا أطلب جدي أي شيء أبداً
Well, two things: Rusty, who was a great hamster
حسناً، شيئين اثنين: رستي، الذي كان هامستر عظيم
and lived a great long life when I was in fourth grade.
و عاش حياة طويلة عظيمة عندما كنت في الصف الرابع
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And a video camera.
آلة تصوير فيديو
I just wanted a video camera.
كنت قثط أريد آلة تصوير فيديو
And after begging and pleading for Christmas,
وبعد الترجي و التمني للكريسماس
I got a second-hand video camera,
حصلت على آلة تصوير مستعملة،
and I instantly started making my own animations
وبدأت باستمرار أصنع رسوم متحركة خاصة بي
on my own,
بنفسي
and all throughout high school I made my own animations.
وخلال سنوات الثانوية صنعت رسومي المتحركة بنفسي
I convinced my 10th grade English teacher to allow me
أقنعت معلمة الصف العاشر أن تسمح لي
to do my book report on Stephen King's "Misery"
أن أقوم بتقريرعن كتاب ستيفن كينج "Misery"
as an animated short. (Laughter)
كرسوم متحركة قصيرة. (ضحك)
And I kept making comics.
و ظللت أصنع الرسوم الفكاهية.
I kept making comics, and at the Worcester Art Museum,
و ظللت أصنع الرسوم الفكاهية، و في متحف وركستر للفنون
I was given the greatest piece of advice by any educator I was ever given.
تم إعطائي أعظم نصيحة قد يستطيع تقديمها معلم على الإطلاق
Mark Lynch, he's an amazing teacher
مارك لينش، هو معلم عظيم
and he's still a dear friend of mine,
و مازال صديق عزيز علي
and I was 14 or 15,
وكنت 14 أو 15
and I walked into his comic book class halfway through the course,
ومشيت إلى محل كتبه للرسوم المصورة خلال الكورس
and I was so excited, I was beaming.
وكنت جداً متحمس، كنت أشرق.
I had this book that was how to draw comics in the Marvel way,
وكان لدي ذلك الكتاب عن كيفية رسم رسوم هزلية بطريقة مذهلة،
and it taught me how to draw superheroes,
وعلمني كيف أرسم الأبطال الخارقين.
how to draw a woman, how to draw muscles
كيف أرسم امرأة، كيف أرسم عضلات
just the way they were supposed to be
بالطريقة التي يفترض أن ترسم بها
if I were to ever draw for X-Men or Spiderman.
لو كنت سأرسم للرجل العنكبوس أو الرجال إكس
And all the color just drained from his face,
وكل الألوان جفت من وجهه
and he looked at me, and he said,
و نظر إلي، وقال
"Forget everything you learned."
" إنسى ما تعلمته."
And I didn't understand. He said, "You have a great style.
ولم أفهم . قال "لديك أسلوب عظيم.
Celebrate your own style. Don't draw the way you're being told to draw.
احتفل بإسلوبك الخاص. لا ترسم بالطريقة التي يقال لك أن ترسم بها.
Draw the way you're drawing and keep at it,
اسم بالطريقة التي ترسم بها و ابق عليها
because you're really good."
لأنك حقاً جيد"
Now when I was a teenager, I was angsty as any teenager was,
الآن عندما كنت مراهقاً، كنت مرتاع مثل ماكان أي مراهق
but after 17 years of having a mother
لكن بعد 17 سنة من وجود أم
who was in and out of my life like a yo-yo
التي كانت تدخل وتخرج من حياتي مثل اليويو
and a father who was faceless, I was angry.
و أب كان بدون وجه، كنت غاضباً
And when I was 17, I met my father for the first time,
وعندما كنت في السابع عشر من عمري، تعرفت على أبي للمرة الأولى،
upon which I learned I had a brother and sister I had never known about.
وفوق كل ذلك علمت أن لدي أخ و أخت لم أكن أبداً أعلم بهم
And on the day I met my father for the first time,
و في اليوم الذي تعرفت فيه على والدي للمرة الأولى،
I was rejected from the Rhode Island School of Design,
تم رفضي من مدرسة رود أيلاند للتصميم،
my one and only choice for college.
اختياري الواحد والوحيد للجامعة.
But it was around this time I went to Camp Sunshine
لكن كان قريب من ذلك الوقت عندما ذهبت لمخيم سنشاين "ضياء الشمس"
to volunteer a week and working with the most amazing kids,
للتطوع لمدة أسبوع والعمل مع أروع الأطفال،
kids with leukemia, and this kid Eric changed my life.
أطفال مع لوكيميا ، و هذا الطفل إيرك غير حياتي.
Eric didn't live to see his sixth birthday,
إيرك لم يعش ليرى ميلاده السادس،
and Eric lives with me every day.
و إيرك يعيش معي كل يوم.
So after this experience, my art teacher, Mr. Shilale,
لذا بعد هذه التجربة، معلمي للفن السيد شاليل
he brought in these picture books,
أحضر إلينا كتب مصورة،
and I thought, "Picture books for kids!"
وفكرت، "كتب مصورة للأطفال!"
and I started writing books for young readers
وبدأت كتابة الكتب للقراء الصغار
when I was a senior in high school.
عندما كنت في السنة الأخيرة من الثانوية.
Well, I eventually got to the Rhode Island School of Design.
حسناً، في النهاية ذهبت إلى مدرسة رود أيلاند للتصميم
I transferred to RISD as a sophomore,
انتقلت إلى أر.أي.إس.دي كطالب في السنة الثانية
and it was there that I took every course that I could on writing,
وهناك أخذت كل منهج دراسي عن الكتابة
and it was there that I wrote a story about a giant orange slug
وهناك كتبت قصة عن رخوي برتقالي كبير
who wanted to be friends with this kid.
أراد أن يكون صديق لذلك الطفل
The kid had no patience for him.
لكن الطفل لم يملك صبر له
And I sent this book out to a dozen publishers
و أرسلت الكتاب إلى عشرات الناشرين
and it was rejected every single time,
وكان يرفض كل مرة ،
but I was also involved with the Hole in the Wall Gang Camp,
لكن كنت أيضاً منضم إلى معسكر عصابة الثقب في الجدار
an amazing camp for kids with all sorts of critical illnesses,
معسكر رائع للأطفال بجميع أنواع الأمراض الخطيرة،
and it's those kids at the camp that read my stories,
وكان أولئك الأطفال في المعسكر من قرأوا قصصي،
and I read to them, and I saw that they responded to my work.
وقرأتها لهم، ورأيت أنهم استجابوا لعملي
I graduated from RISD. My grandparents were very proud,
تخرجت من أر.أي.إس.دي جديّ وجدتي كانوا جداً فخورين
and I moved to Boston, and I set up shop.
وانتقلت لبوسطن، و أسست محل
I set up a studio and I tried to get published.
أنشأت إستديو وحاولت أن يتم نشر أعمالي
I would send out my books. I would send out hundreds of postcards
أرسل كتبي. و أرسل المئات من البطاقات البريدية
to editors and art directors,
للمحررين و مدراء الفن
but they would go unanswered.
لكنها تذهب بلا إجابة
And my grandfather would call me every week,
وجدي يتصل بي إسبوعياً
and he would say, "Jarrett, how's it going? Do you have a job yet?"
ويقول "جاريت كيف تمضي أمورك؟ هل لديك وظيفة؟"
Because he had just invested a significant amount of money
لأنه قد استثمر مبلغ كبير من المال
in my college education.
في تعليمي الجامعي
And I said, "Yes, I have a job. I write and illustrate children's books."
و أقول له "نعم، لدي وظيفة. أكتب و أشرح كتب الأطفال"
And he said, "Well, who pays you for that?"
ثم يرد قائلاً "حسناً، من يدفع لك مقابل ذلك؟"
And I said, "No one, no one, no one just yet.
فأقول" لا أحد، لا أحد، لا أحد حت الآن.
But I know it's going to happen."
لكني أعلم أنها ستحدث"
Now, I used to work the weekends at the Hole in the Wall off-season programming
الآن، كنت معتاد على العمل في إجازات الأسبوع في برنامج ثقب في الجدار خارج الموسم
to make some extra money as I was trying to get my feet off the ground,
لكسب المزيد من المال حتى أقف على قدمي
and this kid who was just this really hyper kid,
و ذلك الطفل الذي كان فعلاً نشيط
I started calling him "Monkey Boy,"
بدأت أناديه "بالولد القرد"
and I went home and wrote a book called "Good Night, Monkey Boy."
وذهبت للمنزل وكتبت كتاب أسمه "ليلة سعيدة، الولد القرد"
And I sent out one last batch of postcards.
و أرسلت دفعة أخيرة من البطاقات البريدية
And I received an email from an editor at Random House
و وصلني ايميل من محرر يعمل في راندوم هاوس
with a subject line, "Nice work!" Exclamation point.
مع سطر عنوان "عمل لطيف!" نقطة تعجب
"Dear Jarrett, I received your postcard.
"عزيزي جاريت، وصلتني بطاقتك البريدية
I liked your art, so I went to your website
أعجبني فنك، لذا ذهبت إلى موقعك
and I'm wondering if you ever tried writing any of your own stories,
وأنا أتساءل هل سبق أن كتبت قصصك أنت
because I really like your art and it looks like there are some stories that go with them.
لأني فعلاً أعجبت بفنك ويبدو أن هناك بعض القصص التي ترافقها.
Please let me know if you're ever in New York City."
أرجو أن تخبري إذا كنت في نيويورك"
And this was from an editor at Random House Children's Books.
وكان ذلك من محرر في راندوم هاوس لكتب الأطفال
So the next week I "happened" to be in New York.
لذا الأسبوع التالي "حدث" أن كنت في نيويورك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I met with this editor,
و تعرفت على هذا المحرر،
and I left New York for a contract for my first book,
وتركت نيويورك للتعاقد على أول كتاب لي.
"Good Night, Monkey Boy,"
"ليلة سعيدة، الولد القرد"
which was published on June 12, 2001.
والذي تم نشره في 12 يونيو،2001
And my local paper celebrated the news.
جريدتي المحلية احتفلت بالخبر
The local bookstore made a big deal of it.
محل الكتب المحلي صنعوا منه شأن كبير
They sold out of all of their books.
باعوا جميع كتبهم
My friend described it as a wake, but happy,
صديقي وصفها بيقظة، لكن سعيدة
because everyone I ever knew was there in line to see me,
لأن جميع من أعرف كانوا هناك في الصف ليروني،
but I wasn't dead. I was just signing books.
لكني لم أكن ميت. كنت أوقع الكتب.
My grandparents, they were in the middle of it.
جدي وجدتي، كانوا في المنتصف
They were so happy. They couldn't have been more proud.
كانوا جداً سعداء. لم يكونوا أكثر فخراً
Mrs. Alisch was there. Mr. Shilale was there. Mrs. Casey was there.
السيدة أليش كانت هناك. السيد شاليل كان هناك السيدة كايسي كانت هناك.
Mrs. Alisch cut in front of the line and said,
السيدة أليش قطعت مقدمة الصف و قالت
"I taught him how to read." (Laughter)
"علمته كيفية القراءة." (ضحك)
And then something happened that changed my life.
عندها شيء ما حدث غير حياتي
I got my first piece of significant fan mail,
وصلني أول قطعة مهمة من إيميل معجب
where this kid loved Monkey Boy so much
حيث هذا الطفل أحب الولد القرد جداً
that he wanted to have a Monkey Boy birthday cake.
لدرجة أنه أراد أن يحظى بكعكة ميلاد الولد القرد
For a two-year-old, that is like a tattoo. (Laughter)
لعمر سنتين ذلك يعتبر مثل وشم. (ضحك)
You know? You only get one birthday per year.
تعرفون؟ تحصل على يوم ميلاد مرة واحدة في السنة.
And for him, it's only his second.
وبالنسبة له كانت، ثاني كعكة.
And I got this picture, and I thought,
و لدي تلك الصورة، و فكرت،
"This picture is going to live within his consciousness
"تلك الصورة ستعيش في داخل وعيه
for his entire life. He will forever have this photo
لطول حياته.ستكون تلك الصورة معه طوال عمره
in his family photo albums."
في ألبومات صور العائلة"
So that photo, since that moment,
لذا تلك الصورة، منذ تلك اللحظة،
is framed in front of me while I've worked on all of my books.
أمامي ويحيطها إطار, خلال عملي على جميع كتبي.
I have 10 picture books out.
لدي 10 صور للكتب الآن
"Punk Farm," "Baghead," "Ollie the Purple Elephant."
"فتى المزرعة"، "رأس حقيبة"، "أولي الفيل البنفسجي"
I just finished the ninth book
وللتو انتهيت من الكتاب التاسع
in the "Lunch Lady" series, which is a graphic novel series
في سلسة "سيدة الغداء"، والتي هي سلسلة رواية صورية
about a lunch lady who fights crime.
عن سيدة الغداء التي تحارب الجريمة.
I'm expecting the release of a chapter book
أنا أتوقع إطلاق كتاب فصلي
called "Platypus Police Squad: The Frog Who Croaked."
يسمى "فرقة شرطة خلد الماء : الضفدع الذي ينقنق"
And I travel the country visiting countless schools,
أسافر عبر البلاد لأزور عدد لامعدود من المدارس
letting lots of kids know that they draw great cats.
لأخبر الكثير من الأطفال أنهم يرسمون قطط رائعة.
And I meet Bagheads.
و تعرفت على رؤوس الحقيبة.
Lunch ladies treat me really well.
و سيدات الغداء يعاملونني معاملة حسنة.
And I got to see my name in lights
و استطعت رؤية اسمي بالضوء
because kids put my name in lights.
لأن الأطفال وضعوا اسمي بالأضواء
Twice now, the "Lunch Lady" series has won
مرتين الآن، سلسلة "سيدة الغداء فازت
the Children's Choice Book of the Year in the third or fourth grade category,
بإختيار الأطفال للسنة في تصنيف الصف الثالث أو الرابع
and those winners were displayed
والفائزون تم عرضهم
on a jumbotron screen in Times Square.
على شاشة جمرترون في التايم سكوير.
"Punk Farm" and "Lunch Lady" are in development to be movies,
"فتى المزرعة" و "سيدة الغداء" في طور أن تصبح أفلام
so I am a movie producer
لذا أنا منتج أفلام
and I really do think, thanks to that video camera
و فعلا أعتقد، شكراً لآلة تصوير الفيديو
I was given in ninth grade.
التي أعطيت لي في الصف التاسع.
I've seen people have "Punk Farm" birthday parties,
رأيت أشخاص يحظون بحفلات ميلاد "فتى المزرعة"
people have dressed up as "Punk Farm" for Halloween,
أشخاص يلبسون كـ "فتى المزرعة" للهالوين
a "Punk Farm" baby room,
غرفة أطفال "فتى المزرعة"
which makes me a little nervous for the child's well-being in the long term.
والذي يجعلني قلق قليلاً على صحة الطفل على المدى الطويل.
And I get the most amazing fan mail,
و تصلني أروع ايميلات معجبين،
and I get the most amazing projects,
و أحصل على أروع المشاريع
and the biggest moment for me came last Halloween.
و أكبر لحظة بالنسبة لي أتت في آخر هالوين.
The doorbell rang and it was a trick-or-treater
رن جرس الباب كانت خدعة-أو-هدية
dressed as my character. It was so cool.
يلبس كشخصيتي. كان ذلك جداً رائع.
Now my grandparents are no longer living,
الآن جدي وجدتي لم يعودوا أحياء،
so to honor them, I started a scholarship at the Worcester Art Museum
لذا لتشريفهم، بدأت برنامج منحة في متحف وركستر للفنون
for kids who are in difficult situations
للأطفال الذين هم في ظروف صعبة
but whose caretakers can't afford the classes.
لكن من يراعيهم لا يستطيع توفير الدروس.
And it displayed the work from my first 10 years of publishing,
و تعرض العمل منذ بداية 10 سنوات من النشر،
and you know who was there to celebrate? Mrs. Alisch.
و تعرفون من كان هناك للاحتفال؟ السيدة أليش
I said, "Mrs. Alisch, how are you?"
قلت " سيدة أليش كيف حالك؟"
And she responded with, "I'm here." (Laughter)
و ردت ب "أنا هنا" (ضحك)
That's true. You are alive, and that's pretty good right now.
ذلك صحيح. أنتي حية، وذلك جيد الآن"
So the biggest moment for me, though,
لذا أكبر لحظة بالنسبة لي،
my most important job now is I am a dad myself,
بالرغم من أن أكبر وظيفة لي الآن أني أب
and I have two beautiful daughters,
ولدي طفلتين جميلتين
and my goal is to surround them by inspiration,
و هدفي هو إحاطتهم بالإلهام
by the books that are in every single room of our house
بالكتب التي في كل غرفة من بيتنا
to the murals I painted in their rooms
إلى الرسومات الزيتية التي رسمتها في غرفهم
to the moments for creativity where you find, in quiet times,
إلى لحظات الإبداع عندما توجد في الأوقات الهادئة
by making faces on the patio
عن طريق صنع وجوه على الرصيف في الفناء
to letting her sit in the very desk
إلى تركها تجلس في الطاولة
that I've sat in for the past 20 years.
التي جلست عليها ال20 سنة السابقة.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً. (تصفيق)